SHANTANOO SINHA

Chicago, IL • (224) 282-5081 • shantanoo.sinha@gmail.com • linkedin.com/in/shantanoo-sinha github.com/shantanoo-sinha • https://shantanoo-sinha.github.io/

SUMMARY

Team player with Masters degree in Computer Science & 9 years of software development experience seeking an opportunity as a Software Engineer. Offering a working knowledge of software development, algorithms, data structures, networks, & databases.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Software Engineer Intern

CME Group, Chicago, USA

May 2020 - Present

- Developed & enhanced internal web application in C#, .Net MVC, MSSQL, Oracle, jQuery, SignalR & Excel libraries
- Programmed complex VBA Macro dashboard reports & integrated with internal application using C#, Oracle & EPPlus
- Created automated testing regression suite in C#, .Net MVC using MSTest reducing manual testing by over 70%

Student Assistant

Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago, USA

September 2019 – May 2020

- Provided technical assistance to students, faculty, staff, tenants, guests, and visitors with the campus technologies
- Troubleshooted software applications, computers, mobile devices, printers, phones AV, printer & plotter issues

Software Engineer

IHS Markit, Noida, India

July 2015 – August 2019

- Devised microservices based architecture using Java, SpringBoot, Hibernate & REST API for the distribution of data to clients
- Implemented a CLI application in Java, HTMLUnit to web-scrape & download 1000+ monthly reports thus saving manual efforts
- Remodeled the UI using Angular 6, Typescript, JavaScript & Bootstrap and improved application performance over 50%
- Reduced application deployment time up to 80% by writing Puppet manifests for 50+ production applications
- Recognized with 'Star Award' & 'Most Valuable Player' award for top performance across the organization

Software Engineer

Tata Consultancy Services, India

December 2011 – July 2015

- Led, supervised technical direction, mentoring and training for a team of 8 software developers
- Developed Timesheet entry & Claim-reimbursement modules using Java, Struts, jQuery, JavaScript & MySQL
- Automated build and deployment by building a generic automated CI/CD pipelines using Jenkins, GitLab & Docker
- Analyzed and optimized complex slow running SQL queries and reduced the running time by 30%
- Awarded 'Star of the Learner's Group' award in a batch of 40 trainees

Software Developer Intern

Sahara India Limited, Lucknow, India

July 2010 – August 2010

- Coded an internal web application tool for Online Letter Processing System using ASP.Net, C#, MS SQL, Visual Studio to store, forward & review official documents electronically and automate management of letters
- Programmed archival process and designed a daily end-of-day batch job to archive old data and files

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

Peer to Peer File Sharing (Java, RMI, Multi-thread, Eclipse, Git, Vagrant, Fedora) Source Code

- Designed a Napster style & decentralized Gnutella style P2P file sharing applications using Java, RMI & multithreading
- Implemented RSA asymmetric cryptography without using in-built APIs for network traffic encryption and improving data security

Bigdata Analysis of Yelp Dataset (Hadoop, Spark, Hive, Pig, Python, Tableau) Source Code

- Analyzed Yelp dataset by creating a data pipeline in Hadoop to import the data in HDFS and Apache Hive
- Transformed the data using Spark & Pig and presented dashboards using Tableau Desktop visualizations

Database Management System (C, Visual Studio, Git, Linux) Source Code

Implemented a small Database Management System in C with a disk-based B+ tree index structure & Buffer Pool implementation

PERSONAL PROJECTS

Flixster (Java, Android, Async HTTP, YouTube Player View, Glide) Source Code

Designed Flixster android app using Java for users to browse movies from the The Movie Database API and watch movie trailers

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Java
- PL/SQL

JPA

- REST API
- jQuery | JavaScript
- GitLab CI/CD | Jenkins

- Android (Java)
- Spring Boot
- Hazelcast Caching
- Bootstrap

- C#
- ASP.Net MVC
- HTML | CSS
- Maven Git | SVN

- Python
- Hibernate
- Angular 6
- Puppet
- Markit (CADIS) EDM

EDUCATION

Master of Science - Computer Science Bachelor of Technology - Information Technology Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago Gautam Buddh Technical University, India 3.5/4.0

August 2019 - May 2021

3.0/4.0

August 2007 - July 2011